Guide to the Cass Gilbert Collection 1883-1952 (Bulk 1900-1934 ) PR 21
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Personal Files, 21541
  - Subseries VIII: Clippings, 21553
    - Clippings related to World War I and Cass Gilbert's Career and His Death, 1917-1937; 21554 (Box 672)
  - Subseries IX: Photographs, 21551
    The small amount of personal photographs in this subseries consist of pictures of family, colleagues, and property.
    - Photographs- Family and Colleagues, Undated, 1918-1928; 21552 (Box 673)
  - Subseries X: Illustrations, 21549
    This subseries includes drawings of architecture including the Parthenon and the Acropolis.
    - Illustrations by Cass Gilbert and Others, Undated, 1918-1931; 21550 (Box 673)
  - Subseries XI. Publications, 21547
    This subseries contains issues of publications regarding Gilbert's personal interests.
    - Publications saved by Cass Gilbert, 1920-1934; 21548 (Box 674)
  - Subseries XII: Other, 21545
    This subseries contains folders of personal materials that do not fit in with the above subseries. It includes passports of Cass Gilbert, papers regarding family genealogy, and his written memories of important events.
    - Other Family Papers, 1911-1934; 21546 (Box 674)
  - Subseries XIII: Bound Volumes, 21542
    This subseries contains letterbooks of personal outgoing correspondence. Topics include expenses, residences, his work on World War I committees, etc. One book contains letters regarding Cass Gilbert, Jr's work with the American Society of the French Legion of Honor. Many of these volumes are fragile and access is dependent upon the judgment of the print room staff.
    - Letterbooks, 1889-1937; 21544 (Volume 392-430)
    - Letterbook, American Society of the French Legion of Honor (Cass Gilbert, Jr.), 1934-1935; 21543 (Volume 431)
- Series V. Lantern Slides, 21527
  The lantern slides include glass slides of some of Cass Gilbert's projects as well as studies of other buildings around the world. The slides are divided into two subseries that reflect Gilbert's numbering of the slides. It appears that the two groups of slides were used for two separate purposes.
  - Subseries I: Woolworth Building, 21539
    This subseries of lantern slides depicts only the Woolworth Building. The images include exteriors and interiors as well as depictions of construction and the finished building. Most of these images are also represented in the photographs in the Woolworth Building section of the Project Files series.
    - Lantern Slides of the Woolworth Building, 1910-1913; 21540 (Box 675-676)
  - Subseries II: National and International Cites, 21528
    This subseries of lantern slides depicts all types of architecture from all over the world including bridges, fountains, parks, museums, and villas. Although a few of Gilbert's projects are represented in this subseries (St. Louis Art Museum, Belle Isle Bridge) most of the slides are not of his work. The slides represent architecture in the United States as well as in France, Italy, England, Holland, Spain, Japan, and Germany.
    - France, Undated; 21538 (Box 677-678)
    - United States, Undated, 1916; 21537 (Box 678-679)
    - Italy, Undated; 21536 (Box 679-680)
    - England, Undated; 21535 (Box 680)
    - Holland, Undated; 21534 (Box 680)
    - Spain, Undated; 21533 (Box 680)
    - Japan, Undated; 21532 (Box 680)
    - Germany, Undated; 21531 (Box 680)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated; 21530 (Box 680)
    - Panoramic Slide of New York Central Park, Undated; 21529 (Box 680)
  - Subseries III: Glass plate negatives, 73336
    - US Custom House, plaster model of Genoa, 73337 (Box 680A)
    - George Washington Bridge, Perspective drawing, John T. Cronin, del (3 negatives), 1926-1928; 73338 (Box 680A)
    - Prelimary study for Supreme Court Building, Longitudinal and transverse sections, John T. Monh, 1929 March 11; 73340 (Box 680A)
    - R.C. Williams & Co. Food Products, R. G. Stickel, del, 1927 June; 73339 (Box 680A)
    - George Washington Bridge, watercolor, John T. Cronin, del., 1930; 73341 (Box 680A)
    - Prelimary study of skyscraper, NYC (2 negatives), undated; 73342 (Box 680A)
    - Drawing of construction site at waterfront, NYC, E.K. Hengerer, 1928 January; 73343 (Box 680A)
- Series VI. Record Books of Drawings, 21523
  The record books contain lists of drawings issued and received by Cass Gilbert. The list assigns a number for each drawing and provides information on the date issued and received, the name of the building, the type of drawing, and a description.
  - Record Books of Drawings, 1906-1909; 21526 (Box 686)
  - Record Books of Drawings, 1909-1913; 21525 (Box 687)
  - Record Books of Drawings, 1913-1920; 21524 (Box 688)
- Series VII. Scrapbooks, 21514
  The oversize scrapbooks contain mostly clippings regarding Gilbert and his architecture projects. Many of these volumes are fragile and access is dependent upon the judgment of the print room staff.
  - Scrapbook (Clippings), 1890-1903; 21522 (Box 689)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings re Architecture), [1893-1898]; 21521 (Box 690)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings and Architectural Drawings), [1886-1900]; 21520 (Box 691)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings and Drawings), 1901-1909; 21519 (Box 692)
  - Scrapbook (Clippings and Drawings), 1925-1932; 21518 (Box 693)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings), 1910-1911; 21517 (Volume 432)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings), 1906-1911; 21516 (Volume 433)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings), 1912-1926; 21515 (Volume 434)
- Series VIII. Metal Printing Plates, 21507
  The printing plates contain images of the Connecticut State Library, the Essex County Courthouse, the US Legation Building, Oberlin College, and the US Custom House. It also contains plates for buildings that are unidentified.
  - Connecticut State Library and Supreme Court Building, Undated; 21513 (Box 694)
  - Essex County Courthouse, Undated; 21512 (Box 694)
  - United States Legation Building, Undated; 21511 (Box 694)
  - Oberlin College, Undated; 21510 (Box 695)
  - United States Custom House, Undated; 21509 (Box 695)
  - Unidentified Buildings, Undated; 21508 (Box 696)
- Series IX. European Sketchbooks, 21502
  This series contains the sketchbooks of architecture that Gilbert studied in Europe. The drawings specifically depict the architecture of England, Italy, France, Spain, Germany, Austria, and the Lowlands.
  - Sketchbook of European Architecture, 1880; 21506 (Volume Vol.1)
  - Sketchbook of European Architecture, 1898; 21505 (Volume Vol.2)
  - Sketchbook of Ironwork in London, 1920; 21504 (Volume Vol.3)
  - Sketchbook of Spanish Architecture, 1925; 21503 (Volume Vol.4)